oh
[Music]
good evening good day everybody welcome
to the latest newest episode of the ask
widget show i hope you're all doing very
well
uh
i know there's a cricket match going on
india pakistan and i'm thankful to all
of you those of you who have chosen to
be here thank you so much
let's see who all is there with us i can
see abhi rishabh
alpha patel rudrak swankit abbay again
pranay rishi anirudh srinivas prabhal
hexin bamboozilys
happy worker explorer and lots of other
people good evening good day to all of
you wherever you are
uh
uh first of all we beg before we begin
uh let me just uh tell you that uh
on the occasion of teacher's day my
course the price is decreasing starting
12 pm tonight
india time
it will be down to 999 for 24 hours only
so in case you were uh
waiting for a price drop or anything or
you're wondering whether you should buy
it if you if you wish to go ahead and
buy it the price will be
at 999 for 24 hours starting 12 midnight
tonight india time so in case you want
it go ahead and do that right
uh so let's go into the questions before
i begin another thing if there's some
noise in the background please forgive
me
there is the festival going on uh what
is it the maha ganesha
in india the festivals are very intense
everyone competes with each other to
have the most intense sound levels
and it goes through any soundproofing
that you can imagine or have and i don't
actually have a soundproof uh studio
so uh do forgive me if there is some
noise that creeps through
all right let's get into the questions
what are the questions for today today
we discussed geopolitics current affairs
history and various other matters let's
see what's the what's question number
one
laksha says do you think the mindset of
russian women is different from the
mindset of western women more
importantly are they traditional and
family oriented like bharathi women in
order to deepen our ties with russia we
should start doing inter-ethnic
marriages between us i call upon my
bharatiya brothers to play a role in
nation building
uh laksha i i as far as i know russian
women are more eastern or more
traditional than western women
the attitudes of western women are kind
of not present
among russian women they are more
traditional minded etc as far as i know
yeah so in case you would like to uh
participate in geopolitics and
contribute to nation building by
marrying a russian lady i i i would say
go ahead if there are any russian
eligible russian young ladies watching
please know that there is this gentleman
young man laksa who is willing
uh reach out if you want and
uh any other bharatiya brothers or
sisters who would like to participate in
this
go ahead go ahead
all right
yes that's one way in which every
citizen can can participate in nation
building and forging geopolitical
relations between
friendly nations go ahead
okay question over yeah all right a
whole lot of questions
aditya says the government indian
government is removing saint george's
cross from the navy looks like the
government is watching my podcast uh
obinov says i'm waiting to see your
reaction on the indian navy flag change
which you mentioned long before happy
yeah i'm happy too
says i distinctly remember somebody
asking you about the union jack insignia
of the indian navy last year it was
about the saint george's cross yeah why
we still have it when when it will be
changed and now within a year that
happened what i thought and what does it
mean at a geopolitical level is it a
sign of better things to come
edward snowden says it seems the prime
minister listened to a podcast and
decided to change the indian navy enzyme
thank you sir so uh i think it's a great
thing i have spoken about this multiple
times if i'm not mistaken about the
colonial artifacts that are still
present in our symbolism in our insignia
navy and
many more things it's not just about the
symbolism
it's about
the various practices and whatnot you
know the entire culture when it comes to
the armed forces is very colonial
especially when it comes to the officer
class yeah many of the practices
traditions and all that they date back
to the colonial times when the british
were ruling india and the indian
armed forces are a creation of the
british so many of those traditions
continue because nobody wanted to mess
with what was already working the indian
armed forces obviously they served the
nation and we are very much proud of
that yeah nobody can dare question their
commitment and their patriotism that's
not that's not ever going to be in
question the only thing is that these
traditions are still continuing and that
kind of is not a good thing yeah
it's been more than 70 75 years now
since india got its so-called
independence yeah 1947
transfer of power so isn't it high time
we remove all colonial artifacts
yes aren't we a proud independent
civilization
so uh what's my thought about the
removing of the saint george's cross the
red cross from the navy great job thank
you so much
i really really appreciate what the
prime minister has done i'm very
grateful incredibly grateful that this
horrific uh like the prime minister said
this this this remnant of slavery
has been finally expunged extricated
excised from the the flag of the indian
navy i'm so glad that happened i'm so
i'm really happy to see that and now we
have uh
an indigenous
symbol uh on the naval flag that dates
back to the maratha navy uh so it's it's
a very good thing very good that these
things are happening
we need to decolonize and like the prime
minister said in the 15th of august in
his address to the nation
we need to decolonize by then
by the time the next 25 years are done
fully decolonized completely thoroughly
entirely so yeah
this is a good beginning what are the
geopolitical
what does it mean on a geopolitical
level
it's it's it sends a message that we are
now uh more
proud of who we are until now we have
been kind of a slave-minded nation yeah
it's true
people refer to the indian slave
mindedness and all there is a
significant element of truth to that and
if you remove all these symbols of
oppression and slavery and colonialism
it kind of frees up people's mindset
they don't have to see that anymore and
that and younger kids who were born
today will never see that and that's
great
so what we are signaling at the
geopolitical level is that we are now
out of the shadow of colonialism
in the past if an indian warship went to
australia went to singapore went to the
uk or went anywhere in the world they
would be still flying that colonial flag
the flag which is the the saint george's
cross that is the english flag on it
that tells the whole world that we are
still colonized right or we're still
very proud of of having been slaves to
the british for
two and a half or three centuries yeah
so that is now gone so it
signals
pride in in being independent and the
throwing off of the last not the last
but some of the shackles of colonialism
it frees up your mind it will uh
probably give a whole different mindset
to the sailors especially the new
sailors who join yeah because they will
never see that that's a flag of slavery
it's great it's great overall
geopolitically it is a signal to the
entire world that we are now no longer
bound by the shackles of colonialism
which we still were until recently
and we still are actually still
continuing there are so many levels at
which mental colonization
happens and it's still there throughout
the indian system the indian state the
indian institutions but this is a good
beginning it's especially relevant in
the armed forces yeah
so uh
i don't know if the government is
watching my podcast or not i think they
don't need to watch my podcast they
would have
wanted to do this themselves at
various levels and it was it was uh it's
something that coincided with the
with the commissioning of the indigenous
aircraft carrier so that probably was
taken as an appropriate opportune time
to make this change so great job
and uh yeah we need to keep keep this
going we need to eradicate all
vestiges of colonialism and slavery from
our institutions from our system from
our minds
in the next 25 years so this is a great
start very
very happy to see this yeah
okay this says weren't the cholas the
greatest seafarers bharata ever
witnessed in its known history yet a
respected chatrapati shivaji is honored
with the title father of the naval
forces please tell us about bharat's
naval history ajay says have you seen
the new indian navy flag they took a
symbol from the maratha navy but it's
not a blue water navy tk okay the most
powerful navy was created by the chula
empire is it not the sikh mentality of
north indian politicians to choose and
only promote their culture and customs
yeah and i had seen some other uh
comment various other comments from some
people saying that um
that india has been betrayed because the
proper maratha flag has not been used
with this with the saffron color and all
that so on the one hand people
from certain regions
some people feel that
we have been betrayed because the chola
in sydney have not been been used some
people feel betrayed because the
proper marathon flag has not been used
here's the deal my dear friends you
can't please everybody
uh
the cholas whether the greater the
greatest seafarers bharat witness we
don't know
we don't know that could have been
greater see
it's like this
before the british took over the country
yeah by various means the greatest navy
that we had was the maratha navy which
was founded you could say by the great
lord chatter pathway right we know that
and then we had great admirals like
kanoji angry and
various of the great
warriors and heroes of india and naval
heroes so the maratha navy was the last
great indian navy
now what we have is the is the
continuation of the british colonial
navy but that's fine now we are putting
our own flag on that it's the it's a
it's it's a version of the maratha in
naval flag right
now before the marathas indeed the
cholas are the greatest navy and they
actually conquered the whole of more or
less the whole of southeast asia up to
the philippines using this great navy so
some could say some people say why is uh
why is chhatrapati shivaji maharaj
called the father of the indian navy why
not rajendra raja rajula well before the
cholas you had samudra gupta who had a
massive navy
he had a great navy so why not him
why not gupta
why not the gupta empire and the gupta
emperors why why do we not call them
the uh fathers of the indian naval
forces before the guptas you have the
the the kalinga empire the seafarers who
indianized the entirety of south east
asia way before the cholas
the cholas were a thousand years ago
kalinga was two thousand years before
the cholas
and they traveled to south east asia
asia
by ship
so should they not be called the fathers
of the indian navy the kalinga the great
kalinga people of kalinga
yeah and before kalinga we had
the vedic age which describes in in the
rig whether there are descriptions which
which vedic text i don't remember there
are descriptions in the vedic texts of
ships with a hundred oars that's a
massive ship yeah so why not the vedic
people and if you talk about the vedic
people being the father of the father
navy well
the vedic people are the ancestors of
all indians so there we go stop fighting
and stop nitpicking about this god damn
things
that's all we do fight among each other
why not this why not there why not this
why not that enough of this nonsense
it doesn't matter we need to remove the
colonial symbols from the indian naval
flag it's done now the government
decided to put the maratha thing great
we are all in some way or the other
we all bear the legacy of the marathas
right
so so what's the problem why do we have
to keep fighting amongst each other all
the god damn time
it's just annoying and it's frustrating
to see indians fighting among each other
for little symbols
whatever symbol has been thrown out that
is what you should celebrate and
whatever symbol
has been used to replace it it's an
indian symbol
own it
and take pride in it that's it
enough of this fighting
okay
rajat says bharat's first aircraft
carrier the first indigenously built of
career ins vikrant has finally been
deployed what's your take on the same is
it going to be an asset geopolitically
and or militarily ananda says
ins vikrant is finally commissioned i
know you've criticized building aircraft
carriers you focus on expanding the
lethality of by submarines and frigates
and all that
rather than concentrating on aircraft
carriers still do you see any positive
outcome of this development if yes what
are they
and how would you like the indian navy
to go about in the next 25 years okay
so first of all let's look at it in this
way
it is a fantastic thing that the
indigenously built and developed and
yeah constructed aircraft carrier ins
vikrant has been deployed commissioned
it is now fully operational it's a
matter of great pride for all indians
understand the achievement
there are only four or five nations that
are capable of building
a warship of that size in that
capability
now india has done it india has
demonstrated it can do it it's a
fantastic achievement as a nation from a
technological perspective from a
military perspective so india has the
capability to build giant warships and
you you can take the same thing forward
and the the ins vikrant is a what what's
the turning display the displays 45 40
000 tons 45 000 tons you can extend the
same technology and make an 80 000 ton
warship
so it tells you what india is capable of
what india's engineers and builders etc
scientists all that uh naval designers
and naval builders are capable of it's
fantastic so it it tells the world that
india is at that level the top the elite
uh engineering and naval engineering
nations in the world yeah we are we are
there it's great
uh is it is this aircraft carrier going
to be an asset geopolitical or military
see let's understand the the role
and and the relevance of aircraft
carriers
aircraft carriers when was the last time
an aircraft carrier was used in in an
actual hot war between evenly matched
nations second world war
that's the last time aircraft carrier
saw proper combat between two evenly
matched forces and look at the
casualties on both sides how many
aircraft carriers are at the bottom of
the seas yeah so aircraft carriers are
difficult to
uh
defend in the
when you are evenly matched aircraft
carriers have a certain relevance
they are very relevant in peace time
when you are a massive nation
and you want to project force
in various parts of the world so let's
say you are the united states you are a
superpower and you want to demonstrate
to smaller nations that we are the big
dog out here and you dare not market us
so then you send your aircraft carrier
sailing around yeah
and that nation knows they dare not
touch it or do anything about it and the
very
size and scale and the number of
aircraft it carries it is intimidating
it's scary
a single ship can
can essentially annihilate a whole
nation that sort of thing
but
will the americans dare to send an
aircraft carrier close to chinese
held waters
they do it in the
taiwan
south china sea et cetera but you know
when when there is
when there are military tensions they
will keep their credit carriers far away
from there so aircraft carriers are
great as a show of force as a show of
how powerful you are but they don't
really they're really hard to defend
there are so many different ways in the
21st century that you can take out an
aircraft carrier yeah so in a hot war
you actually have to hide aircraft
carriers that's how it is so aircraft
carriers geopolitically etc it's good
for patrolling and projecting power and
you know things like that you cannot
really use it in the war unless you are
want to take a massively significant
risk of losing this enormous aircraft
and all the enormous warship and
whatever aircraft are
are sitting on top of that
so uh
i hope we are not going if so we how
many do we have now we've got two
aircraft carriers
the navy wants a third one it says see
typically in in
in the navy if you have three ships one
is going to be operational one is going
to be traveling to its deployment or
from the deployment back to the port and
one will be undergoing refits so if you
have three ships only one will be
operational at a time typically on
average
so if you have 300 ships
you can understand that about 100 are
currently deployed and operational right
that's how it is so if you have two
aircraft carriers it's possible
sometimes both will be under undergoing
refits or repairs or overhauling so
typically you would want three aircraft
carriers and in that case one will be
definitely deployed at all times that's
how it is so the navy is saying we want
more
i think it's not a good idea to invest
billions of dollars worth of money in
building a new aircraft carrier one more
yeah maybe in the future when india
crosses the trent 10 trillion dollar
economy mark then most nations will be
will be unwilling to antagonize india
that's when you can have one more carry
on project power right now india needs
submarines submarines are way more
lethal that's what the the late general
bipin robert said
we need submarines
but yeah well
some people in the navy they they enjoy
the prestige that an aircraft can give
them
yeah
so it's also about the the the fact that
the nature of canada is an extremely
prestigious warship you are the
commander of an aircraft carrier you
have the highest prestige in the indian
navy and one of the highest prestige
most prestigious positions in the entire
indian military that's great so people
aspire to have that so if you're more
curious more people can do that there is
an element of selfishness in every
individual understand that
but from the national interest
perspective we want the navy to be as
lethal
as possible
and
you want to distribute that lethality
not concentrate the lethality into into
large warships
imagine that you have a massive amount
of investment just in one warship
somebody takes it out it's you you lost
one third of your navy right there but
if you can distribute that lethality
across the oceans
yeah let's take a look at the map to
understand what i mean by distributed
lethality yeah
let's see let's take a look at the map
where's the map here's the map come on
bring it on
so look at the indian ocean region
that is the region of interest for india
from the malacca straight over here to
the uh gulf of aden to the hormuz strait
the gulf the persian gulf and the
greater indian ocean region which
includes the maldives the diego garcia
region and so on so forth uh all of that
is india's region region of interest
the indian strategic planners etc they
call it india strategic backyard well
you can give it any name you want but
unless you actually own it
it will not be your strategic back yet
and how do you own something by
patrolling it constantly if you have one
massive ship can you patrol this entire
region no but if you invest in lots of
smaller vessels smaller ships naval
vessels missile both submarines
then you can have lots of different
assets distributed all across this
region constantly patrolling
right and if you're patrolling you're
visible and everyone knows just by
seeing your presence there that this
belongs to you this there are so many
indians out here which means this is
indian territory
or india this is india's backyard but if
there's only two or three ships in the
entire region then well no one cares
they will not consider this to be india
by karen they will they will be
emboldened and encouraged to encroach
into these regions like the chinese are
doing so what india needs is numbers
numbers quantity quantity has a quality
of its own that's what joseph stalin
said he was right
we need quantity with quality first
build quantity we need lots of
submarines we i i say we need at least
60 70 or maybe 100 submarines why not
get cheap submarines get cheap
submarines build keep submarines a
submarine does not need to cost 500
million dollars or a billion dollars you
can get a hundred million dollar
submarines and i'll speak about this
again yeah
and some people say it's not possible to
have a submarine of 100 million dollars
what are you people smoking you people
know nothing
right so here it is this is a massive
region we need numbers we need quantity
we need to patrol this entire region in
in large numbers 24x7 imagine you are
you are a policeman
and your job is to uh
is is to
your job is to uh
uh keep the peace in your neighborhood
you can keep the peace only if you have
five or six different police cars
patrolling it 24x7 but if there's no
police car visible there then the the
criminals will be emboldened right
imagine there's a city in which there is
no police patrolling at all well then
crime will rise but if you have lots of
police patrolling 24x7 very visible then
crime will go down obviously similarly
in the indian ocean region if there are
lots of indian warships always visible
then automatically it becomes your name
your your strategic backyard and your
enemies whoever they are your
adversaries will be scared to come out
in numbers or even they will they will
want to come out very very you know very
silently and stealthily
they will not be emboldened to just make
an appearance and and push people around
like the chinese are doing right now so
india needs numbers numbers numbers
in the next 25 years india needs to
build numbers lots of different kinds of
warships not just one class destroyers
corvettes corvettes submarines
especially the submarine is the most
effective 21st century naval warship
it's not visible it's very hard to
detect it's it's it can stay deep
underwater it can attack at will it can
it can
launch cruise missiles ballistic
missiles torpedoes it can take out
warships it can take out cities it can
take out ports it can even launch nukes
it can do everything and it's it's very
well hidden and camouflaged it takes
very good technology to be able to
detect and track submarines only a few
nations can do that so india needs to
invest in submarines and also on surface
vessels
not aircraft carriers for the price of
one aircraft carrier you can have i
don't know 100 missile boats missile
boats are so cheap disposable and they
can be so deadly look at the last
engagement in india held with pakistan
what is it 1971 the karachi harbor india
took out the karachi harbour using
missile boats chip cheap missile boats
that is the kind of distributed
lethality we are talking about
as cost efficient as possible as
numerous as possible and as deadly as
possible distributed over a wide
surface area of the ocean that's what
india needs to do you build aircraft
carriers you're gonna
pour in so many of your funds right into
just one warship yeah
we already have
unsinkable aircraft carriers let me
demonstrate what those are what are the
unsinkable aircraft carriers the entire
andaman archipelago each of these
islands can be an unsinkable aircraft
carrier you can make you know air force
bases here
you cannot sink these islands similarly
in the luxury pylons you have more
unsinkable aircraft carriers you build
some naval base
air force bases there you may have to do
a little bit of reclaiming of the sea
you know constructing uh extending the
islands
like the chinese have been doing sure
why not do that so that is what india
needs to do
we already have unsinkable aircraft
carrier why why do we need to build
invest billions of dollars on these
massive warships
use that money
to create actual distributed lethality
right so that's what i would say that's
where india needs to go in the next 25
years i hope it happens
and uh
okay aman raj says
uh we now know that the lift of the ins
vikrant cannot fit the rafal so we will
have to forcefully fly by the f-18 why
was this not considered while designing
it was it a short-sightedness
the ins vikrant has two lifts you know
elevators
for
so in a let's take a look at what this
uh
uh warship looks like ins vikrant
uh let us put that on the screen so that
we can understand what we are discussing
over here
ins vikrant so uh
do we have
a schematic or something
uh
okay so typically this is what the
aircraft carrier looks like if you can
see uh it's a multi-storage
ship
and you will have aircraft right now
it's it's it doesn't have any aircraft
on it right now
but you will have aircraft on the uh
surface level of the ship you know
parked over there and you will have some
aircraft that that will be under the
surface inside the ship
and to those will be the aircraft that
need some refits or or some some small
repairs or whatever yeah some
overhauling so those aircraft will be
taken below the deck and all that work
will be done under the uh below the deck
so there will be compartments and
hangers below the deck where you can
keep some aircraft and you can work on
them the mechanics can work on them so
to bring those aircraft from under the
deck to the actual flight deck there
will be a couple of elevators so i'm not
sure if they're visible here or not the
thing is this
these elevators have a certain width now
we know that the rafale it's a wingspan
the the breadth of the
wings is about i don't know 10.9 meters
something like that yeah
and the f 18 is is nine point something
meters
and so on so the the uh elevators of our
aircraft carrier the latest one
are
i believe too narrow to accommodate the
rafale
so unless the french can provide rafal
aircraft which have foldable wings the
rafale
unless the french can do that we will
not be able to put rafael on this
aircraft carrier that's for sure
the f-182 is just barely able to make it
by a few centimeters here and there so
even that would not be actually a good
idea so what what kind of aircraft would
actually fit comfortably in these
elevators it would either be the mig-29
which india already uses yeah
or
a future version of the pages fighter
plane so there was a deck based
fighter that india
a naval version of the they just was
proposed it was it was the prototype one
or two prototypes were built and they
were able to land on these aircraft
carriers that was demonstrated the
ability
so maybe that but the navy has rejected
the the naval version of the pages so
that seems to be out of the question and
maybe a future twin engine deck based
fighter that is currently under
development you know a future version of
the pages family aircraft that sort of
thing so either india buys a few f-18s
30 40 whatever yeah american aircraft
which are reasonably good or india
continues with the mig-29s which are
well it's a good aircraft but it's a
kind of
kind of old aircraft yeah so that's the
two options india has right now either
invest in more
mig-29s or buy the f-18 and make it
somehow work on that on those narrow
elevators
or ask the french to provide rafales
that have folding wings in that in which
case everything works fine maybe the
french can do that or then wait for the
twin engine deck base fighter which is
another seven eight years in the i don't
know how how long it will take maybe by
20 30 20 20 and 20 to date i'm not sure
so these are the options we have now
what what's the reason why we we
developed we we designed or we built
these elevators these lifts that were
narrow and too narrow for the rafale
i'm not sure what was the reason for
that
uh
maybe the the the aircraft carrier was
designed a long time ago
ago i am not
sure what the history is
but that's where we are maybe it was on
purpose maybe we did not want certain
aircraft or maybe there is some
agreement between india and france that
they will provide rafales with folding
wings or whatever
or maybe india just wanted to go ahead
with the mig-29
or maybe india wants to appease uncle
simon by 20 30 40 whatever f18s i'm not
sure so yeah that's where we are so
that's what the these are the options
that india has vis-a-vis the ins vikrant
if it is operational now we need
aircraft on it obviously i think it can
carry 30 aircraft which is a reasonably
okay number yeah
so it will be
so let's see what india goes for these
procedures take a long time long time
long time long time i hope they speed it
up and make it operational as soon as
possible so the so that
uh the warship is now operational it can
flow it can sail wherever it wants
but it still needs its contingent of
fighter planes
so that's the next step so i'm not sure
let's let's see what decision the
government makes
uh if if the french can provide rafa's
it's great rafales with folding wings
because india already uses reference the
rafale is an excellent jet no doubt
about it
so ideally the french gave us rafales
with folding wings and that would be the
best
possible option for india
okay summer says what's your opinion on
africa's offer to india as they cannot
repay certain loans should india go
ahead with the
offer so what offer is being mentioned
over here
uh so india has been offering lines of
credit to various african nations uh the
total line of trade i believe is about
30 or 40 billion dollars thus far around
30 35 40 billion dollars
roughly yeah the actual number may be
closer to 30 billion dollars somewhere
in that ballpark
figure
so it's it's it's not one nation it's a
it's it's multiple nations that india
has offered credit lines to so what is a
line of credit we need to first
understand that there is a difference
between a loan and a line of credit what
the chinese do is they offer loans with
very harsh repayment uh
requirements the rates of interest are
very high and it's it's it's typically a
given that that nation will not be able
to repay it but what they the chinese do
is that they also bribe the various
dictators
you know who run these nations so the
dictator gets a nice hefty paycheck
straight away lump sum maybe a few
million dollars here and there and that
makes them happy and then they sign the
agreement and then the nation has to
eventually find a way of repaying the
the the debt or the nation has to say as
to give off parts of its actual
sovereign assets to china that is the
standard debt trap that the chinese use
in order to colonize africa now india
doesn't do that india offers lines of
credit what is a line of credit it's
like having a credit card you you
let's say you have a credit card with
hypothetically one lakh credit limit so
you have a credit card which you can
use up to a limit of one lakh rupees
let's say right
now you can choose to never use it your
choice
or you can choose to
make a purchase what's worth ten
thousand rupees so ninety percent of
your credit limit is still uh empty so
you've taken
taken a loan essentially from the credit
card company for 10 000 rupees and then
you repay it within a certain whatever
the the conditions are right there will
be a certain
rate
uh interest rate and a certain time
period within which you repaid and you
can i think there you can
you can choose to
pay pay a certain amount of it every
month something like that right so it's
it's a very flexible arrangement so you
can choose to never use it you can
choose to spend only some part of it and
use only some part of the credit limit
or you can choose to
use the credit limit to the maximum it's
your choice entirely it's a very
flexible arrangement so a line of credit
is just like that
so india let's say india offers a
certain african nation a one billion
dollar line of credit so the african
nation can use it
and and the there are certain terms and
conditions on it
the
typically the term that india
gives to the african nations is that if
they use the line of credit for whatever
amount of money they need to purchase
whatever goods material services they
are purchasing with this credit from
indian companies so that benefits india
in that way but the interest rates
typically on this line on these lines of
trade that india offers are low
nowhere close to what the chinese do so
these are very generous
uh terms that india offers it is in no
way predatory in nature
very low interest rates and very
flexible arrangements and often india
has even forgiven certain certain deaths
if they are not too high you know it's
happened in the past that india has
forgiven certain depths that's because
the african nation whatever it was is
not in a good condition and that sort of
thing so india because of this
this arrangement what india is offering
india has a very high amount of goodwill
in the african nations yeah and they do
realize that taking uh
loans or these lines of credit from
india is way better than going for china
for for chinese investments because that
is going to end up you're going to end
up selling your nation your nation's
sovereignty piece by peace to the
chinese
so now what's happened is that certain
african nations
have
are in a position where they can't quite
pay back the loans
or whatever they've taken in credit so
what they have offered is they have
opened up their lithium
lithium mines to indian companies and
investments so they will pay back in
terms of lithium lithium ore or or
actual lithium from their mines so that
is the offer that sir i'm not sure i
don't think it's been disclosed which
african nations have made this offer but
it's more than one
and these uh i think we can find out
which african nations are rich in
lithium yeah but they have made this
offer to india that we are unable to pay
back the cash so why don't you
uh take repayments of whatever we have
borrowed from you in terms of lithium or
or actual lithium so they are opening up
the releasing mines to indian companies
to come and invest there in india the
indian companies then can then take back
the lithium
based on whatever rate it is and all so
that you they and that will be
considered to be repayment of the debt
so i think it's it's a very good uh
offer they have made
they have in no way been forced to make
the offer it was their their choice yeah
the the indian
like i said the the lines of credit are
very generous and
not
uh predatory at all so these african
nations have offered lithium to india in
exchange for what they owe india in
terms of what they've borrowed i think
it's a very good thing for india and
india should make use of this
opportunity and
build these
investments in african nations have
indian companies work in the mines and
invest in the mines and maybe develop
the mines further and india can take
back some lithium and we can use that as
a repayment and that can be an ongoing
arrangement even after the debt is
repaid we can we can buy purchase
lithium from these african uh nations if
if india builds the mining
infrastructure further develops the
developers develops it further and all
that
so i think it's a win-win situation for
these african nations for india as well
because lithium is uh one of the things
that's very much in demand um all the uh
new
electric vehicle technology and all that
it depends on lithium-ion batteries yes
your your cell phone typically uses a
lithium-ion battery the tesla electric
vehicles they use lithium-ion batteries
uh your laptops have lithium-ion
batteries lithium is is a very big deal
these days yeah and some of the african
nations are very rich in lithium so it's
great for india so this is something
they have done of their own volition
they have not been coerced into doing
this they have not been armed twisted
into making this offer i think it's a
very good offer we need to work out the
terms with them and i think india should
go ahead with that it's a very good
arrangement and it's a win-win for both
sides so overall a very positive and
good development
okay harsh says bharat recorded the
quarter growing rate
okay the first quarter of 2022 the gdp
of india grew at 13.5 percent but then
there are some articles in various
publications that are say that it's
disappointing or whatever why why is
that okay
so yeah uh
the past two years were kind of bad
years globally for all economies lots of
economies actually shrank india's
economy also shrunk in 2020 i believe to
a significant percentage yeah because of
the uh kovid
incident the kovit pandemic the
lockdowns that ensured all the
businesses went down
globally and india also suffered from
that yeah
now in 2022 in the first quarter the
economy has grown at 13.5
in the first quarter that's the figures
that have been put out so india's
economy has again gone has again started
expanding it has already gone
ahead of its 2020 mark and india's
economy overall has now
surpassed the overall economic
economy of the uk so india is now the
fifth largest economy in the world the
uk is number six
before that india was number six uk was
number five so india's economy is again
growing very well 13.5 in the first
quarter that is very very uh encouraging
uh
and if you can sustain this sort of
growth growth even ten percent even
eight percent plus growth for the next
20 years india is going to be a really
massive economy in 20 years in just one
generation's time yeah
so i think it's it's very good uh and
the indian government did not heed the
advice of all the western economists and
indian born western economists like
abhijit banerjee amartya sain and the
incredible mr raghuram rajan who were
making certain recommendations to india
yeah as to how india should proceed with
its economy during the lockdown during
the pandemic india did not do that india
was fiscally very prudent and now you're
seeing all the western economies which
did those things they are kind of in the
doldrums they are seeing negative growth
they are saying they are witnessing
recession and they are witnessing
shocking rates of inflation india is
going through none of that india is
doing very well so india the indian
government the prime minister the
finance minister et cetera
they did the right thing in in there was
you know a slowdown of the economy that
was inevitable but now india is surging
ahead 13.5 growth is incredible
incredible very very encouraging very
positive uh thing for india it looks
like india may cross five trillion
dollars dollars by 2025 by the end of
2025. india seems to be on target for
that so that is in extremely good
development india the outlook is very
positive for india india is one of the
few nations in the world right now that
can be optimistic about the future the
long-term future right india has a young
population in india as a booming economy
there is so much infrastructure
development needed in india so much
growth potential in india overall very
positive some articles say it's
disappointing they can go to hell who
cares it's the same old tired people who
keep on
harming about everything that goes that
happens in india if something goes wrong
they will they will shout it from the
they will tom tom it from the tops of
the mountains if something is good they
will try to portray it something
disappointing ignore those people
we know who the usual suspects are we
know what the publications are ignore
those people look at the numbers
don't look at people's opinions
don't look at people's interpretations
everybody knows everybody has an opinion
ignore opinions just look at the hard
numbers and then you can make your own
judgments using the goddamn intelligence
that god gave you
all right so i don't care whether some
people are disappointed and whether some
people have written long articles so
that it's nothing great and all that
they
are jealous
and they are disappointed that india is
doing well yeah so india is doing very
well the economy is growing
it's growing
faster than what i had hoped for which
is i'm extremely pleased to see that and
let's uh let's keep this going yeah
india will most likely most likely seems
to be on track to eclipse the 5 trillion
dollar mark by 2025 and then the next
figure is 10 which we need to all work
towards yeah so this is great
very good development and especially
good nice to see us eclipse the uk the
former colonial oppressor yeah
so they are experiencing 0.2 growth or
something like that or 1.2 percent good
whatever it is and we are witnessing
more than 10 times the growth
good good for them
okay sushi kant says what is your take
on india participating in a vostok land
drill but not part of the sea drill is
india doing the right thing according to
you okay so what is the watchtop thing
so russia
has these uh military exercises
that happen that take place every year
so there is the zapad exercise zapad the
word zapat means west in russian there
is the exercise which happened last year
2021 zapad21
this year we have the vostok22 vostok
the word warstock means east in russia
so zapad vostok center which means
center and kavkaz which means the
caucasus region of russia which is the
south part of russia let's go to the map
and take a look at what it means
so where is the map the map is here
so the caucasus region is over here the
black sea caspian sea region and the
land mass between that that is the
caucasus region that's where typically
the kavkaz exercises take place
the uh zapad exercises take place in the
west of russia
in which includes belarus the the last
time in last year i think belarus was
also part of that and various nations
take part so we had vostok which is in
the west
uh
sorry zapad in the west kavkaz in the
south center is typically somewhere in
the central region of russia and vostok
happens in the far east of russia these
are strategic level military exercises
not tactical level these are large scale
military exercises and they serve to
demonstrate
they serve many purposes
they serve to demonstrate russia's uh
overall capabilities military
capabilities using all the various
branches of the military the
the
the army the navy the air force and
whatever else is involved yeah
and various nations take part in it they
see they serve to uh prove various
military strategic concepts and various
tactics and strategies they are planning
to use in
in
in an actual war and it has all these
multiple purposes and many nations
especially nations that are friendly
with russia participate in this exercise
so this year we have the vostok 22
exercises which are happening in the far
east summer here
of russia so india is participating in
the even the chinese i believe are
participating in this
and india is participating in the
land-based uh exercises not the sea
based exercises so like i said there is
army navy air force all of that is
involved so there will be some component
of this happening at sea some of it on
land and so on so forth so india is
participating in the land-based
portion of the vostok uh exercises
so well
it's good
india doesn't have to participate in
everything and obviously there is the
the pressure from the u.s the americans
are obviously not happy that india is
participating at all
so what's the what's the point of all
this so first of all it demonstrates it
serves to demonstrate to the russians
that we are very much
friendly with you
and we consider to consider you to be a
friendly nation and we trust you enough
to
to participate in joint exercises with
you yeah
it's a signal to russia india and russia
always have had very good relations very
warm relations and not fake warm
relations out of political experience
geopolitical experience but actually
very warm people to people relations
dating back 70 plus years even even
longer than that so india and russia
there is a significant element of trust
which is rare in geopolitics so india is
participating and and this is the
signaling that going to russia that we
trust you and we are we are a friendly
nation and we consider to you to be our
friends and that sort of thing
to the us
it sends a message that we may be
working with you but we will always look
out for our own interests you may not
like the fact that we are doing these
exercises with russia but we're going to
go ahead and do it so deal with it that
is the message india is sending to the
u.s
it is india is sending a message to the
chinese that you may be currently in in
good terms with russia but we are also
here we are also part of this and you
can't do a thing about that that's the
message messaging to china now if india
is not participating in the entire
spectrum of exercises it's also a small
concession to the us that we will
participate but we will not take part in
everything so india is playing the
multi-polar game india is saying we will
engage with multiple people with
multiple powers and we will look out for
our own interests so the americas they
don't like it that's their problem but
we will also give a small concession to
the u.s and not by not participating in
the sea based exercises and that sort of
thing
yeah so that's the kind of
messaging and signaling india is doing
to multiple nations it is the
multi-polar game but at the end of the
day india is going to look out for its
own national interest and that is what
everybody needs to keep in mind that is
the biggest message that's going out
to everybody
so that that's what's happening over
here
okay ud says what are your thoughts on
the last president of the ussr mikhail
gorbachev was he someone who genuinely
cared about the welfare of his people
such that he willingly accepted western
values or was he a western stooge who
crumbled the ussr deliberately and
allowed american mncs into his country
for his own great for his own gain aryan
says what do you think of mikhail
gorbachev is he really the greatest
peacekeeper is claimed by the west and
if the soviet union had not collapsed
should the world have been more or in
order now
if you want to see
where mikhail gorbachev stood
yeah just see who praised him the most
when he died
who praised him the most when he died it
is the west that praised him the most
when he died was there any praise forth
coming from the former ussr
i don't think there was any phrase for
forthcoming from there so it shows you
that the people of the former ussr the
people of russia etc
they do not hold mr gorbachev in very
high regard
the truth is that they they regard him
as a sellout and western storage as a
traitor essentially to their own people
what did mr gorbachev do he presided
over the
end stage weakening of the ussr he did
this perestroika and glasnost reforms in
which
essentially it was self-criticism
admission that the russian regime the
russian system is not good and the
western system is better actually that
sort of admission so that that caused
the further ideological weakening of the
ussr
and then he presented over the actual
dissolution the breakup of the ussr
eventually the ussr became so weak that
various republics the central asian
republics etc they succeeded they
declared their independence and there
was nothing the ussr was willing to do
about it in the past if anybody dared
say a word about it there would be tanks
in that
the next day in in that region
tanks military tanks that's happened so
you know there is an element of force
when it comes to geopolitics when it
comes to holding your nation together
yeah and mr gorbachev uh
presided over any and and he essentially
ensured that the ussr breaks up in
fragments
and
so yeah he you you could consider him to
be a western student the russians
certainly considered him to be western
stooge here
and whatever he did
ended up destroying the the soviet
nation and the russian economy after him
it was a
it was this very mediocre person called
mr yeltsin who came to power and
mr yeltsin came to power because of all
the
deeds that mr gorbachev himself did he
mr gorbachev set the stage for someone
like yeltsin to come to power mr yeltsin
was even more of a western stooge he
deliberately and systematically
destroyed russia's economy
systematically destroyed everything the
russian the ussr had built up over 70 is
whatever 50 60 70 years whatever yep
so that's what happened uh
if he wasn't the greatest peacekeeper no
he was not a peacekeeper i mean he he
handed everything over to the west
that's what it did so that's why the
west loves him very much mr gorbachev's
greatest legacy is that pizza hut ad
uh i'm sure you can still see it on
youtube just just type in gorbachev
pizza hut that was his greatest legacy
selling out the russian economy to the
western mncs
so the russian economy was destroyed
during yeltsin's time and mr gorbachev
was making ads for pizza hut asking
russians to to to to put money into
western mncs yeah so that's his legacy
overall a very mediocre person the
person who presided over the destruction
and the dissolution of the ussr i'm not
saying the ussr was a great thing it was
oppressive in in a lot of ways on its
own people and various other other
nations as well that's true but any
great nation any great superpower has
elements of this to it yeah
so overall his legacy is like nothing
nothing to write home about
okay asmitha says what's your take on
various claims and reports on china's
illegal occupation since 2020 of some of
the indian territory in ladakh whether
it is indian territory or disputed land
along the lse which is in between what's
the best course of action for india in
this matter
see the chinese have encroached onto
into indian territory since the 1950s
yeah they have been doing this
and they have refused to demarcate the
border so now now what we have is that
the indian army and the indian nation
ensures that the chinese don't come
beyond a certain line they are always
constantly trying to push forward now
the situation is reasonably stable there
are these incursions that happen i think
india is also doing certain actions of
its own into the the territory that the
chinese claim to be their own yeah
that's there's this
ongoing tug of war
everything china occupies is illegal the
chinese occupation of tibet itself is
illegal right
now some media reports keep coming in
that the chinese are building a village
in indian occupied in indian territory
or they have encroached three kilometers
here or three kilometers there
and typically these media reports come
from various certain certain
quarters
which are very much anti-india i'm
talking about the indian media yeah
there are certain elements of the indian
media the legacy media there are very
much anti-india and anti-whatever
whatever political dispensation is in
power today right their overall approach
is nt india and they are often on the
payroll of their various outside forces
i'm not taking any names you can leave
it to your imagination if you want to
yeah and they typically come up with
these reports and when you fact check
the reports you will realize that
whatever village is being built is on
territory they have been occupied for a
very long time
for a very long time that's what's
happening recently some just last week
or this week itself reports appear in
twitter of some some video of chinese
soldiers doing something on indian
territory and when you fact check that
that again it you realize it's on their
side of the lac the line of actual
control
so
these media
agencies have been doing this constantly
trying to make the indian public lose
faith in the indian military in the
indian government
what's actually happening now is that
india is in the strongest position in
the past so many decades vis-a-vis china
india has
taken a very hard line approach to any
chinese incursion we saw it in in the
various clashes that happened in the
past two three years there was a doklam
thing in which india stood firm and
refused to allow china to enter into
into the territory that is bhutanese
certainly here yeah
then we had the uh
uh the the the clash that happened uh in
which 20 indian soldiers had died in
like 3 000 chinese soldiers died not 3
000 but like 50 or maybe 100 yeah they
have tried to cover it up the chinese
and that sort of thing so india is
standing very firm this government has
had the most hardline approach against
chinese incursions and aggression of of
any government we can think of yeah
so uh
so the thing is this
don't depend on the media don't believe
everything the media says
what's actually happening at the lsc is
not supposed to be known
okay it is not it is not for us to know
it these things they have to be kept
kept secret by the government for
various reasons for national security
reasons because
there are elements within the indian
nation within the indian population who
are we know that they are in some ways
anti-india there is the 2.5 front war
that very high-ranking people have
spoken about there are elements within
india you know
so we cannot reveal everything to the
indian population certain things are
always kept under wraps no matter which
nation you're in whether it's the us
whether it's russia whether it's china
whether it's france whether it's
switzerland whether it is the uk there
are things that concern national
security and they are kept secret from
your own public for the good of the
nation and the long-term prosperity and
national interest yeah so and there will
always be
certain elements within your nation that
will that will try to serve foreign
interests look at who is funding these
various media outlets look at where the
sources of funding are and then you will
know just you just have to follow the
money but nobody has that will do the
due diligence and the people will
believe
whatever is being said so here's the
deal
don't trust everything the media is
throwing at you the media wants
sensationalism the media much of the
media is anti-india the indian media
much of it
unfortunately
the best course of action for india is
to grow its economy
if you grow your economy you will grow
your military if you grow your military
chinese will be more and more vary of
trying to tangle with india simple
solution it's a simple solution to all
the problems the best course of india
action for india is to focus on growing
its economy and then correspondingly
making its military more and more
powerful that is the only solution to
all the problems whether we china with
any other nation
yeah
prajwal says what's your opinion on
mount kailash a sacred place for hindus
being currently part of chinese occupied
territory okay let's take a look at
where mount kailash is
it's in the himalayas north of india
it's in tibet essentially what we now
call tibet
i apologize for the incredible noise
that's that's coming in but that's just
how it is
mount kailash where is mount kailash
let's take a look at mount kailash
and they have some goddamn chinese name
over it right now
kang green walkway peak or whatever
so it's over here
right
so
it is mount but it did but google is now
giving it a chinese name
right google is banned in china but
google gives it a chinese name can you
believe it so that makes you question
what google is actually doing
and if you remember google's boss is an
indian
funny things going on so mount kailash
is over here
yeah it is in tibet chinese occupied
tibet it is the one of the holiest
places in hinduism in buddhism in
journalism in the born religion of tibet
and perhaps the sikhism i'm not sure
what is him
whether the sikhs continue consider
mount kilaus to be sacred or not i'm not
sure about that
but certainly in hinduism buddhism
jainism which is all
the dharmic umbrella yeah so mount
kerala is one of the most sacred sites
it is the abode of lord shiva himself
and it is currently in chinese occupied
territory what is my opinion about this
i think it is completely unacceptable
unacceptable it is a shame
for all indians as long as you are
living and breathing if mount kailash is
occupied by the chinese
and the mans are over lake
it is a matter of great shame for us
and we need to
take proactive measures to ensure that
this illegal and despicable
occupation of this holy site is ended as
soon as possible how do we end the
occupation of the of of mount kailash by
the chinese by growing easy india's
economy
making it cross trend trillion dollars
of in value that where india's military
might will will increase and then we
will be able to evict the chinese from
tibet
that's the solution to all the problems
right
so work on that
okay rahu online says
at present our subcontinent including
all neighboring countries are facing
many natural calamities
despite criticism of the dedicated
voters sri modiji is showing compassion
verbal and materialistic towards all
nations even to enemy nations what is
the significance of this geopolitical
move what's your take big bro
okay
so what what uh is being asked
essentially is the the situation in
pakistan in pakistan right now you have
this terrifying terrific terrible
flooding that's happening
uh i heard more than a third of the
of the
nation was underwater
a couple of days ago i'm not sure what
the situation is today so mr modi uh
prime minister modi had tweeted
condolences and and uh
that sort of thing you know to the
pakistanis think that it's terrible this
has happened and we wish you well and
that something of the
to that effect you know
a compassionate tweet about what's
happening in pakistan and maybe there
was the possibility of india sending
some material aid maybe monetary aid
financial aid or some other kind of aid
to pakistan it's not been decided yet
whether it's gonna be done or not but
yeah there is a possibility that india
may send some aid to pakistan in in its
hour of need so lots of people are upset
lots of people say it's a terrible thing
we are feeding the snake we are feeding
our enemy the child the pakistanis have
always indulged in terrorism against
they want india destroyed they want
india dead but why are we helping them
see it's like this
whatever aid india gives to pakistan if
it if if we actually send some aid to
pakistan it's not going to be a massive
amount of aid it's going to be maybe
10 million dollars worth maybe 100
million dollars which in the grand
scheme of things is peanuts yeah
now it's like this
when you have an enemy
that you want to
beat up
in the future
and maybe you want to dismantle the
enemy completely yeah you want to
annihilate the enemy in the future
so there's this guy this bad guy
you are planning
you have a plan in your mind you gotta
beat him up and you gotta dismantle him
in the future
what you should do right now is appear
to be very compassionate to him
yeah offer aid say nice things so that
in the future if there is a fight
between you and him people will remember
that all of this that you have always
been nice
see before the uh bala court thing
happened prime minister modi made it a
point to actually visit the pakistani
prime minister's house once right an
unscheduled stop to
into pakistan he met mr sharif he even
went to his grand mr sharif's
granddaughter's wedding and he blessed
the the girl and her husband and that
sort of thing so it was a very nice
compassionate peace peaceful gesture
so when in when you do all this you
demonstrate to the world that you are
trying for peace and then in the future
when there is a fight or war you can
always say that we tried our best we
tried our best don't blame us
right so if today india gives some aid
to pakistan and some nice tweets are
forthcoming
why are you getting upset about it
in the future we will deal with them as
they need to be dealt with
it's coming
i have always said this i'll say it
again pakistan is a temporary nation why
do i say pakistan is a temporary nation
because it's going to be dismantled
i wish the people of pakistan all the
best i have no nothing against them i
wish them all the best i wish them
happiness and prosperity to them and
their children but the nation of
pakistan is an evil terrorist nation
it will be dismantled by the indian
state
it's coming it's not far
so when you are planning that
when you are planning that sort of thing
it it is nice to to to make all these
gestures
yeah
so that the world the media will will
always
have to
make this up or make a point of saying
it but india has always tried to fight
for peace and india has made all these
various gestures we india even gave aid
to the pakistanis in the time of need
but see how pakistanis are behaving
so that's how it is that is the
geopolitical significance of these moves
all right so don't get upset about these
these are
in these are small gestures they don't
cost much to india all right
okay peeking owl says
sorry to say
sorry to say abhijit you're completely
wrong there are no submarines in the
world that cost 100 million dollars each
sub at least costs 700 plus million
dollars submarines are expensive as well
a budget you're completely mistaken and
completely misguided and wrong
though i completely agree
with him that aircraft carriers are
obsolete
this was a naval exercise between the
u.s navy and sweden there was the naval
exercise between the u.s navy and sweden
the swedish navy actually sunk
a nuclear aircraft carrier with a cheap
diesel electric submarine by passing the
whole carrier strike group this was a
naval exercise not a war it was not an
actual sinking it was a it was a fake
sinking let me show you what
what we're talking about
there is this article
okay in one of the very prominent
american publications the national
interest let's read out from this
sweden's super stealth submarines are so
lethal they sank a u.s aircraft carrier
sank in quotes what does it mean
so this article is from 2016 november
2016. six years ago less than six years
ago five and a half years ago
in 2005 the uss ronald reagan a newly
constructed 6.2 billion dollar aircraft
carrier sank after being hit by multiple
torpedoes fortunately this did not
happen in actual combat it was simulated
as part of a war game
pitting a career task force including
numerous anti-submarine escorts against
hsms gotland a swedish submarine a small
swedish diesel-powered submarine
displacing 1 600 tons
yet despite making numerous attack runs
on the reagan the gotland was never
detected
this outcome was replicated time and
time again over two years of war games
with opposing destroyers and nuclear
attacks on marines succumbing to the
stealthy swedish submarine
naval analyst norman polmar said the
gotland ran rings around the american
carrier task force
and so on so forth the u.s specialist
anti-submarine specialist but
demoralized by the experience right
so how was the gotland able to evade the
reagan's elaborate anti-submarine
defenses involving multiple ships and
aircraft employing a multitude of
sensors
and even even more importantly how was a
relatively cheap submarine costing
around 100 million dollars
roughly the cost of a single f-35
able to accomplish that okay so that's
what the article says
so there you have it this submarine cost
a hundred million dollars
a hundred million dollars in 2016. maybe
it costs 120 million dollars today six
years down the line considering
inflation
it's a possibility but i was right that
submarines do cost a hundred million
dollars one of the best submarines in
the world the swedish gotland class
submarine costs only around 100 million
dollars that's how cheap and inexpensive
it is it is a diesel electric submarine
right
so uh yes it was a naval exercise which
was repeated multiple time times over
two years and every time this submarine
was able to evade the anti-submarine
defenses of the entire aircraft carrier
strike group it was able to penetrate
the defenses and take out the
uh us aircraft carrier in a simulated
exercise that tells you that a single
submarine can take out aircraft carriers
that's how vulnerable aircraft carriers
are today and that also tells you that i
was right that a submarine can indeed
cost just 100 million dollars the same
price as an american f-35 fighter plane
which is the point which i was always
making why doesn't in india invest in
cheap
in cheap submarines
in cheap inexpensive submarines why
can't india do that
an aircraft carrier costs at least 5
billion dollars you can have 50
submarines for that for the price and
see how lethal good submarines are so
that's why india needs to invest in good
submarines maybe india should buy this
swedish submarine company which produces
the gotland class submarines
and that sort of thing i apologize for
the noise
i can't hear myself that's how it is
anyway
okay sure did goel says i guess the
government has listened to the advices
and they've tasked coaching shipyard
limited to construct 16 attack boats
which will be equivalent to strength
brigades
these boats will be capable of carrying
at least four to six cruise missiles
each with a mounted gun system i am so
very satisfied by the navy's design
bureau
yeah i think it's a good thing i don't
know if they've listened to me or not
but yeah
there are 16 attack boats i think these
are anti-submarine warfare ships
light smallish ships that are being
built you can call them attack boats or
anti-submarine warfare cruisers or
whatever
stealth frigates or whatever 16 of them
have been being built and i think they
will be all operational or at least
constructed by 2026 2026 it's a very
good move
like i always keep saying we need
numbers numbers quantity is a quality of
its own
and this is a very very good and
important step in that direction yes
so yes 16 uh
warships are being built and it's a very
good thing i am also very happy and
satisfied to see this and these will be
uh but they will i'm sure they will
carry cruise missiles maybe the brahmos
missile and they will also have
anti-submarine capabilities which means
there'll be submarine killers by design
so that's a great thing so this is a
very positive step it's a positive step
in the right direction we need a lot
more of that we need more submarines as
well so yeah good good we are seeing
some good things happening
okay raghav bharadwaj says what do you
make of the current state of the indian
air force
with the migs mirages jaguars close to
being phased out don't you think we are
not too concerned about it as much as we
should be there has been no significant
update
and so on and so forth so and so forth a
long story
uh please make yours the questions
shorter please i really request you
uh
what's the question what's the state of
the air force okay what is the currency
of the air force the indian air force is
not where it should be we need a lot
more planes
we have 28 29 squadrons that are
operational right now
the the sanctioned state
the number is we need at least 10 12
squadrons more
i think we need 40 plus quadrants the
more the more planes you have the better
you are as an aircraft air force i don't
mind india having a 1000 fighter plane
air force what's wrong with that
the more you have the better better off
you are the chinese look at the look at
the strength of their air force they
have well in excess of
a thousand fighter planes some of them
may be older some of them may be close
to being obsolete but they have the
numbers they can deploy them when needed
the more aircraft you have the better
you are as a nation as an air force so i
think india needs to stop going for lots
of different kinds of aircraft we have
like like i said over here the jaguars
the mirages the pages the rafale
and what not
so i think we need to uh if we if we
mix also mig-21s and so on
so i think we need more aircraft as a
stop-gap measure we can we can perhaps
buy more files because we are already
operating close with 36 rafals we will
have 36 very soon we should perhaps go
in for 36 more maybe 100 more if
required if we can make them fit on the
aircraft carrier yeah so i think if we
do purchase more foreign aircraft there
is this uh mrfa tender about purchasing
foreign aircraft if we go for that we
should do it quickly we should acquire
more rafales not the f-16 not anything
else just there are files because we
already operate that if we have too many
different aircraft we need to have lots
of different supply chains for spare
parts and all it's a it's a logistical
nightmare
so go for more files maybe 36 more maybe
100 more whatever is whatever makes
sense in the meanwhile develop the
indian indigenous aircraft the pages
mark ii the amca you know advanced
medium fighter aircraft and whatever
else
so that's what needs to happen and i
hope we are we're in good shape by 2030
let me take a let me take a look at the
comments what people are saying are you
able to hear the noise outside i mean
the thickest of walls are defeated by
this noise
okay what do we have there's nothing
much nothing much about the noise
all right all right all right let's go
back
yes
[Laughter]
yeah so that's what i'm enjoying right
now yes
yes
okay
going back to the question man
says what are your views on neville
chamberlain
do you think he was the person who tried
until the end to prevent the second
world war
or was he weak as he gave hitler the
impression of non-aggression
while he was out annexing countries like
austria and
czechoslovakia or neville chamberlain
was one of the uh one
see one can see his entire career and
his actions in hindsight now
yeah
he turned out to be one of the well
weakest one of the weaker
uk prime ministers
you could say that he sold out
sold out to hitler he appeased hitler
when there was
when that when the time called for
strong measures resolute measures he
indulged in appeasement against adolf
hitler in 1938 the nazis were
threatening to invade the swadanthan
land region of what is now
it was once part of the austro-hungarian
empire
then it was part of this new nation of
czechoslovakia because which was born
after the end of the first world war
right
so the german
majority region called sweden land was
part of czechoslovakia and hitler said
that it should be part of germany and he
was threatening to invade czechoslovakia
and take over this within the land and
then there was this entire
threat of war again in europe so this
guy neville chamberlain
the prime minister of the uk he made i
think three trips to to germany to
negotiate with uh adolf hitler and try
to uh preclude the possibility of war
and at the end of the third trip he came
back to london he was met on the airport
on the airport tarmac by journalists and
he was brandishing this piece of paper
saying that see i have hitler's
signature he will not go to war
and there was a big concession that was
made to the germans that swedenton land
would go back to germany that sort of
thing
so at the end of the day he was not able
to prevent war because the next year
germany invaded any way
they invaded chicago they invaded half
of poland the
soviets took the rest the other half of
poland and that all led to
the second world war so if his intention
was to stop a war from happening he
failed completely and he made his
country look very weak and docile
and he essentially was seen as somebody
who tried his best to appease adolf
hitler and at the end of the day none of
that bore any fruit
so that's that's the truth about devil
chamberlain whether we like it or not
okay i'm not sure if you can continue
like this it's way too noisy
yeah very
all right okay let's let's take some
more questions
man
says which mistake do you think proved
more expensive for napoleon bonaparte
okay let's just continue i uh
let's just
the thing is i can't hear myself anyway
says which mistake do you think proved
more expensive for the poland bonaparte
firstly invading the russian empire
which resulted in the loss of
approximately six hundred thousand
soldiers
or removing the spanish royal dynasty
and placing his own brother as the ruler
of spain
which eventually led to the peninsular
war a kind of guerrilla war which
resulted in thousands of deaths of
french soldiers
uh in my opinion
the mistake which was the most which was
the worst mistake was the attempt to
invade russia
so napoleon
attempted to invade russia he actually
was able to capture moscow but it was a
victory that gave him nothing
because the russians deliberately
withdrew from moscow but not after
burning the city down
the russians burned the city down the
city of moscow and then they left the
city and they said okay napoleon go
ahead enjoy your victory in a burnt out
city so napoleon i think he spent a
month or so in moscow
not enjoying it at all because he had
got nothing the russians kept on
withdrawing from withdrawing from the
french they adopted a scorched earth
policy destroying all the farmland
destroying all the villages so that the
french could gain nothing see when you
are invading
a territory you have to live off the
land
you have to get your resources your food
stuff everything from the land you are
invading and conquering
and if you can't do that you lose you
know it doesn't work
so yeah that's what happened and uh
at the end of the day the french it was
a huge disaster for the french
especially because the onset of the
russian winter which
claimed
i don't know hundreds of thousands of
french soldiers at the end it was a
disaster and it precipitated the decline
of napoleon as a ruler and it led to his
eventual defeat yeah
okay so that's where we are i think i'm
gonna have to stop this because it's
just too noisy i can't even hear myself
so we're gonna stop this here a little
prematurely but it's just too noisy over
here
so uh
yeah
i have many more questions but i don't
think i can take them i can't hear my
own
my own
voice
should i take more questions do you want
me to take i i think i'll stop you know
all right we're going to end it here
thank you very much all and next week i
hope there will be no
no such noise
so until next week take care thank you
and bye